Stocking Brown, Patricia; Papers apap203
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Patricia Stocking Brown Papers
1895-2003
1981-1999
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Brown, Patricia Stocking, 1942-2004
apap203
7.39 cubic ft.
This collection documents Siena College professor Dr. Patricia Stocking Brown's (1942-2004) research and scholarship in biology as well as her breast cancer advocacy, research, and education work.
19
8
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Stephen C. Brown and Bonnie Spanier donated all materials in this collection to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives in 2005 and 2006.
Biographical History
Dr. Patricia Stocking Brown was born on April 25, 1942 in Cadillac, Michigan. Her collection file and papers reveal that she was the first female professor of the sciences at Siena College as well as a historian of women in science, a feminist, and advocate for breast cancer research. Dr. Brown's specialty was in zoology, especially the endocrinology and kinesiology of amphibians.
Dr. Brown earned her bachelor's degree, master's degree, and PhD in Zoology from the University of Michigan in 1963, 1966, and 1968 respectively. In 1969, Dr. Brown became a professor of Biology at Siena College where she was head of the department from 1984-1986 and 1988-1991. Throughout her career, Dr. Brown was the recipient of several fellowships and research grants, as well as an active member of groups such as the American Society of Zoologists, the American Society of Ichthyologists and Herpetologists, the Endocrine Society, and the Association of Women in Science. Dr. Brown also published numerous papers regarding amphibians, often with her husband, Dr. Stephen C. Brown, who was a professor of Biology at the University at Albany.
Outside of her scientific research, Dr. Brown was a historian and advocate of women in science. Her projects included researching married biologists in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, developing exhibitions of said female biologists, and publishing articles on women herpetologists and ichthyologists. Dr. Brown also became an advocate of breast cancer research after her own diagnosis. From 1997-2004, she was the founder and co-president of the Capital Region Action Against Breast Cancer (CRAAB!), which provides support and information for those diagnosed with breast cancer and their care givers, and also co-founded the New York State Breast Cancer Network, a coalition of grassroots breast cancer groups which held the inaugural Breast Cancer Advocacy Day in 1999.
Dr. Brown lived in Altamont, New York and died at home in 2004 of breast cancer. In 2008 donors from the Women's Studies and Biology Departments established The Patricia Stocking Brown Fund for Feminist Social Justice Research in University Libraries at the University of Albany. This award supports and promotes graduate and undergraduate student research in feminist social justice through use of collections in the University at Albany M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains Dr. Brown's scientific research data, manuscripts, and poster session materials; historical research correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, and exhibit research; and advocacy education materials. There are also a number of oral interviews on cassette tapes relating to her historical research as well as breast cancer lectures on video cassette tapes. However, no papers solely pertaining to CRAAB are located within Dr. Brown's papers.
The collection also includes manuscripts co-authored with Dr. Brown's husband, Dr. Stephen C. Brown, a Professor Emeritus from the University at Albany. Additional materials relating to Dr. Brown's advocacy work, including CRAAB and the New York State Breast Cancer Network Coalition, can be found in the Bonnie Spanier Papers, UA-902.073.
Please note the overall dates and series dates for this collection are not inclusive.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series: 1 - Historical Research: 1895-2002, Undated; 2 - Scientific Research: 1968-1987, Undated; 3 - Advocacy and Education: 1991-2003, Undated; 4 - Audio-Visual Materials: 1983-1999, Undated.
Women; Medicine and Health Care; Women biologists--New York (State)--Albany; College teaching--New York (State); Breast--Cancer--Research; Patient advocacy--New York (State); Correspondence; Exhibit scripts; Files by subject; Research (documents); Brown, Patricia Stocking, 1942-2004; Siena College; CRAAB! (Albany, N.Y.)
- Historical Research, 1895-2002; 1; 6.01 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains research notes, correspondence, photographs, manuscripts, and exhibit research pertaining to Dr. Brown's historical work on women scientists. The series also includes source materials from the late 19th century and early 20th century used by Dr. Brown in her research.
  - Fellowship Application, National Science Foundation, VPW, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 1)
  - ASIH Conference Exhibit, General Correspondence, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 2)
  - ASIH Conference Exhibit, General Research, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 3)
  - ASIH Conference Exhibit, Alice Boring, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 4)
  - ASIH Conference Exhibit, Grace Pickford, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 5)
  - ASIH Conference Exhibit, Various Women Scientists, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 6)
  - American Philosophical Society Library, 1995 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 7)
  - American Society of Zoologists, Early Women PhDs, Correspondence, 1978-1981; 1989 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 8)
  - American Society of Zoologists, Early Women PhDs, Lists, Research, Undated (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 9)
  - American Society of Zoologists, Misc. Correspondence, Tapes Information, 1978-1982 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 10)
  - American Society of Zoologists, Silfer, Eleanor, 1979; 1981 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 11)
  - Bailey, Florence and Vernon Biography, Correspondence, Research Notes, 1991-1992 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 12)
  - Bailey, Florence, and Vernon Family History-Bailey, Hiram, 1895 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 13)
  - Bailey, Florence, and Vernon Family History-Bailey, Vernon, 1906; 1930; 1937 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 14)
  - Bailey, Florence and Vernon Family History- Other, Undated (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 15)
  - Bailey, Florence, and Vernon Photographs, Undated (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 16)
  - Berkeley Seminar, Early Women Biologists, 1980 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 17)
  - Conference and Workshop Events, 1995; 1998; 2002 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 18)
  - Bern, Howard Biography, Interview, 1991; 1997-2002 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 19)
  - Bern, Howard Interview, Correspondence, Research, 1956; 1995-1998 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 20)
  - Cochran, Doris, 1950; 1986; 1992 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 21)
  - COPEIA Article-Additional Materials, 1952; 1955; 1986-1988; 1993-1994 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 22)
  - COPEIA Article-British Women Scientists, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 23)
  - COPEIA Article-Conant, Isabelle, 1987-1988 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 24)
  - COPEIA Article-Jordan, David Starr, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 25)
  - COPEIA Article-Correspondence, Women Scientists, 1987-1998 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 26)
  - COPEIA Article-Manuscripts, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 27)
  - Couples Project-Incomplete Manuscript, 1990; 1992-1993 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 28)
  - Couples Project-Manuscript Edits, Undated (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 29)
  - Couples Project-Comstock, Anna Botsford Biographies, Research, Undated (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 30)
  - Couples Project-Eigenmann, Rosa Smith Biography, Correspondence, Research, 1986-1988; 1992 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 31)
  - Couples Project-Gaige, Helen Thompson Biographies, 1956; 1962; 1968; 1999; 2001 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 32)
  - Couples Project-Gaige, Helen Thompson Correspondence, 1981-1999 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 33)
  - Couples Project-Gaige, Helen Thompson Research Notes, 1992; 1999; 2002 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 34)
  - Couples Project-Gaige, Helen Thompson Photographs, Undated (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 35)
  - Couples Project-Gaige, Helen Thompson, Rogers, James Speed, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 36)
  - Couples Project-Harvey, Ethel Brown Biography, Correspondence, A-C, 1949; 1951; 1964; 1991 (Box 1 (1-Historical Research), Folder 37)
  - Couples Project-Harvey, Ethel Browne Correspondence D-V, Biographies-Organizations, 1979; 1991-1992; 1995 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 1)
  - Couples Project-Schrader, Sally Hughes Biography, Fellowship Application, 1998-1999 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 2)
  - Couples Project-Schrader, Sally Hughes Correspondence, C-N, 1991-1992; 1998 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 3)
  - Couples Project-Schrader, Sally Hughes Correspondence R-Colleges, Obituary and Will, 1978; 1991-1992; 1997 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 4)
  - Couples Project-Schrader, Sally Hughes Diaries; Lederberg, Joshua Solomon, 1992; 1999 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 5)
  - Couples Project-Schrader, Sally Hughes Exhibit Materials, 1998 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 6)
  - Couples Project- Wright, Anna Allen Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 7)
  - Couples Project- Wright, Anna Allen Photographs, Undated (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 8)
  - Early women ASZ members, exhibit materials (1 of 3), Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 1)
  - Early women ASZ members, exhibit materials (2 of 3), Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 2)
  - Early women ASZ members, exhibit materials (3 of 3), Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 3)
  - Early women scientists, exhibit materials, Undated (Oversized 3, Folder 4)
  - Environmental Biology of Fishes Article Correspondence, Research, 1986; 1989; 1995-1996 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 9)
  - Environmental Biology of Fishes Article, Requests for and Copies of Manuscript, 1987; 1989; 1993-1995 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 10)
  - Evans, Herbert and Simpson, Marion, 1981 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 11)
  - Exhibit label titles, Undated (Oversized 3, Folder 1)
  - Data Analysis, Unknown Project, Undated (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 12)
  - Grey, Marion, 1986-1987 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 13)
  - Howland, Ruth, 1930; 1940; 1947-1948 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 14)
  - Institutional Correspondence, British Universities, 1988 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 15)
  - Institutional Correspondence, Bryn Mawr, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 16)
  - Institutional Correspondence, JLB Institute of Ichthyology, 1995 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 17)
  - Institutional Correspondence, Royal Society of London, 1979; 1982-1983 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 18)
  - Institutional Correspondence, University of California, Berkeley, 1981 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 19)
  - Institutional Correspondence, Various, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 20)
  - Merriam, Clinton, 1942 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 21)
  - Moore, Emmeline,Moore Correspondence, Research, 1922-1943; 1996 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 22)
  - Moore, Emmeline, Brown Correspondence, 1926; 1985-1988; 1994-1996 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 23)
  - Moore, Emmeline, Brown Manuscripts, 1994; 1996 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 24)
  - Moore, Emmeline, Photographs, Undated (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 25)
  - Moore, Emmeline, Brown Research, 1937; 1986; 1996 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 26)
  - Museum Work, 1996 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 27)
  - Museum work, exhibit materials, Undated (Oversized 4, Folder 4)
  - Oversized exhibit labels, Undated (Flat-file 1)
  - Oversized exhibit labels, Undated (Flat-file 2)
  - Parallel Lives: Women Who Worked with Their Husbands, exhibit materials, Undated (Oversized 4, Folder 3)
  - Research and materials from exhibit on early women scientist, including their work in museums, education, and alongside husbands who also were scientists, Undated (Oversized 1)
  - Rhode Island Normal School, Undated (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 28)
  - Sally Hughes Schrader and Franz Schrader, exhibit materials, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 4)
  - Sally Hughes Schrader and Franz Schrader, exhibit materials, Undated (Oversized 3, Folder 2)
  - Various Photograph Copies, Undated (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 29)
  - Various Photograph Copies, Notes and News Article, Undated (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 30)
  - Various Scientist Couples, Undated (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 31)
  - Various Women Scientists, A-G, 1986; 1989-1990; 1993-1994; 1996 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 32)
  - Various Women Scientists, A-D, Photographs, Undated (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 33)
  - Various Women Scientists, G-M, Undated (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 34)
  - Various Women Scientists, P-W, Undated (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 35)
  - Various Women Scientists, British, 1988 (Box 2 (1-Historical Research), Folder 36)
  - Various Women Scientists, Foreign, Undated (Box 3 (1-Historical Research), Folder 1)
  - Various Women Scientists, Local, 1984; Undated (Box 3 (1-Historical Research), Folder 2)
  - Various Women Scientists, Negatives, Undated (Box 3 (1-Historical Research), Folder 3)
  - Various Women Scientists, Slides, Undated (Box 3 (1-Historical Research), Folder 4)
  - Women and Gender in Science Conference, Correspondence, Manuscripts, 1994-1995 (Box 3 (1-Historical Research), Folder 5)
  - Women PhDs in zoology, exhibit materials, Undated (Oversized 4, Folder 1)
  - Women scientists who worked in other countries, exhibit materials, Undated (Oversized 3, Folder 3)
  - Women scientists who worked in other countries, exhibit materials, Undated (Oversized 4, Folder 2)
- Scientific Research, 1968-1987; 2; 0.90 cubic ft.
  The series documents Dr. Brown's scientific work and collaborations, and includes research notes, applications, manuscripts, and materials from one poster session.
  - Amphibian Facility Proposal, 1968 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 1)
  - ASZ Conference Materials, 1971; 1985-1986 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 2)
  - Brown and Brown, Newt Research, 1971 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 3)
  - Bartell, Frye, and Snyder, Salamander Research, Undated (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 4)
  - Brown and Brown, Newt Research, 1972 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 5)
  - Brown and Brown, Newt Research, 1976 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 6)
  - Brown and Brown, Taricha Tarosa Newt Research, 1979 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 7)
  - Brown and Brown, Tarichaorosa Newt Research, 1981 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 8)
  - Brown, Brown, Bisceglio, and Lemke, Newt Research, 1982 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 9)
  - Brown, Brown, and Frye, Plethodontid Salamander Research, 1979 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 10)
  - Brown and Frye, Frog Research, 1968 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 11)
  - Brown, Giuliano, and Hough, Turtle Research, 1973 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 12)
  - Brown, Hastings, and Frye, Plethodontid Salamander Data, 1977 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 13)
  - Brown, Hastings, and Frye, Plethodontid Salamander Research, 1977 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 14)
  - Brown, Hayner, Bania, and Brown, Salamandrid Research-Edits, 1984 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 15)
  - Brown, Haynor, Bania and Brown, Salamandrid Research, Submission, 1984 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 16)
  - Conferences, 1978-1987 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 17)
  - COPEIA Manuscript, 1980 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 18)
  - Fellowship Applications, 1967-1970 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 19)
  - Frog Pigment Manuscript, Research Data, 1969 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 20)
  - Frog Pigment Manuscript, 1969 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 21)
  - Frog Pigment Manuscript, Research Data, 1975 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 22)
  - Frog Pigment Manuscript, 1975 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 23)
  - Murphy, Michael, Recommendation and Thesis, 1978; 1981; Undated (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 24)
  - Newt Research, Raw Data, 1972-1976 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 25)
  - Plethodontid Salamander Data, 1976 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 26)
  - Pteridines Research, 1973-1975 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 27)
  - Pteridines Research, Undated (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 28)
  - The Relationship Between Body Water and Growth During Larval Development and Metamorphosis in Wood Frogs, poster materials, Undated (Oversized 4, Folder 5)
  - Turtle Research, 1973 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 29)
  - Various Research Slides, Undated (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 30)
  - Various Theses (other authors), 1970 (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 31)
  - Water Balance Manuscript, Undated (Box 4 (2-Scientific Research), Folder 32)
- Advocacy and Education, 1991-2003; 3; 0.10 cubic ft.
  The series primarily includes materials related to breast cancer advocacy, research, and education. It features curriculum material for courses taught at Siena College, files about advocacy events, an award speech, as well as a presentation on breast cancer. Please note that this series included several floppy disks containing materials complementary to (and sometimes duplicates of) the paper files. As there were a small number of files, the archivist elected to print out the materials on disk and inter-file them with the original paper materials. Then the archivist saved all of the Microsoft Word documents on disk as PDFs on CD. This CD is available for review by researchers.
  - 1998 Review of Breast Cancer Course (Box 4 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 33)
  - Activities Associated with Breast Cancer Memo, 1998 (Box 5 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 34)
  - Application for Summer Stipend for Development/Revision of Biology of Breast Cancer, 1999 (Box 6 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 35)
  - Breast Cancer Presentation, Undated (Box 7 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 36)
  - Breast Cancer: Women Making a Difference Winter Forum, 2000 (Box 8 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 37)
  - Grant Application Materials, Undated (Box 9 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 38)
  - Harvey Fellowship Application, 1999 (Box 10 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 39)
  - Inspirational Quotations, Undated (Box 11 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 40)
  - Journal Clubs, 1999-2000; Undated (Box 12 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 41)
  - Komen Award, 1998 (Box 13 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 42)
  - New York State Breast Cancer Network Advocacy Day, 2000 (Box 14 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 43)
  - New York State Breast Cancer Network, New York State Health Science Board, 1999 (Box 15 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 44)
  - Siena College, BIOL 025, Undated (Box 16 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 45)
  - Siena College, BI 40 Seminar, 1996; Undated (Box 17 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 46)
  - Siena College, BI 58 Seminar, 1991; 1993 (Box 18 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 47)
  - Siena College, BI 90 Seminar, 1995 (Box 19 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 48)
  - Siena College, BIOL 490 Seminar, 1995; 1999-2000; 2003; Undated (Box 20 (3-Advocacy and Education), Folder 49)
- Audio-Visual Materials, 1983-1999; 4; 0.38 cubic ft.
  Arranged chronologically by media type.
  The series contains oral interviews on audio cassette tapes related to Dr. Brown's historical research, breast cancer educational lectures on video cassette tapes, and an oral interview of Dr. Brown on audio cassette tape.
  - Interviews, George, Carl and Riley, Ed, 1983 (Cassette 1)
  - Interviews, Spanier, Bonnie and Dr. Brown, tape (1 of 2), 1987 (Cassette 2)
  - Interviews, Spanier, Bonnie and Dr. Brown, tape (2 of 2), 1987 (Cassette 3)
  - Interviews, Schrader, Sally Hughes, Lancefield, Donald and Rebecca by Manning, Kenneth, 1987 (Cassette 4)
  - Interviews, Scott Allan and Peggy at Woods Hole, 1991 (Cassette 5)
  - Interviews, Baylor, Ted, and Martha, 1991 (Cassette 6)
  - Interviews, Hastings, Woody, 1991 (Cassette 7)
  - Interviews, Inoue, Shinyu, 1991 (Cassette 8)
  - Interviews, Schroeder, 1992 [sides 1 and 2/3] (Cassette 9)
  - Interviews, Schroeder, 1992, [3/3] (Cassette 10)
  - Interviews, Schroeder, 1992 (Cassette 11)
  - Interviews, Been, Howard, 1997 [sides 1 and 2/3] (Cassette 12)
  - Interviews, Been, Howard, 1997 [3/3] (Cassette 13)
  - Interviews, Been, Howard, 1998 (Cassette 14)
  - CRAAB Breast Cancer Course, 1998 (1 of 2) (Cassette 15)
  - CRAAB Breast Cancer Course, 1998 (2 of 2) (Cassette 16)
  - Vox Pop Susan, BC/CRAAB, Spanier, Bonnie, Brown, Pat, Enck, Judith, 1999 (Cassette 17)
  - Interviews, George, Carl, and Riley, Ed, Undated (Cassette 18)
  - Interviews, Gonzales, Helen Schif on Ralph Muss, Undated (Cassette 19)
  - Dr. Pat Brown, Review of Breast Cancer (1 of 2), 1998 March 28 (Video-tape 1)
  - Dr. Pat Brown, Review of Breast Cancer (2 of 2), 1998 March 28 (Video-tape 2)
  - 1998 Breast Cancer Course, tape #2, 1998 March 21 (Video-tape 3)
  - Pat Brown's Breast Cancer Course (1 of 2), 1998 April 4 (Video-tape 4)
  - Pat Brown's Breast Cancer Course (2 of 2), 1998 April 4 (Video-tape 5)
  - Pat Brown, PhD, 1998 Breast Cancer Course, 1998 April 18 (Video-tape 6)
  - Pat Brown, Cancer Course (1 of 2), 1998 April 25 (Video-tape 7)
  - Pat Brown, Cancer Course (2 of 2), 1998 April 25 (Video-tape 8)